      UNIT VI




      REPRODUCTIO




        Chapter 1                Biology in essence is the story of life on earth. While individual 
        Reproduction in Organismsorganisms die without fail, species continue to live through 
                                 millions of years unless threatened by natural or anthropogenic 
        Chapter 2                extinction. Reproduction becomes a vital process without 
        Sexual Reproduction in   which species cannot survive for long. Each individual leaves 
        flowering Plants         its progeny by asexual or sexual means. Sexual mode of 
                                 reproduction enables creation of new variants, so that survival 
        Chapter 3                advantage is enhanced. This unit examines the general 
        Human Reproduction       principles underlying reproductive processes in living organisms 
                                 and then explains the details of this process in flowering plants 
        Chapter 4                and humans as easy to relate representative examples. A related 
        Reproductive Health      perspective on human reproductive health and how 
                                 reproductive ill health can be avoided is also presented to 
                                 complete our understanding of biology of reproduction.



















L










                                                          4


                                       2021-22

                      Born in November 1904 in Jaipur (Rajasthan) Panchanan Maheshwari 
                      rose to become one of the most distinguished botanists not only of India 
                      but of the entire world. He moved to Allahabad for higher education 
                      where he obtained his D.Sc. During his college days, he was inspired 
                      by Dr W. Dudgeon, an American missionary teacher, to develop interest 
                      in Botany and especially morphology. His teacher once expressed that 
                      if his student progresses ahead of him, it will give him a great satisfaction. 
                      These words encouraged Panchanan to enquire what he could do for 
                      his teacher in return.
                         He worked on embryological aspects and popularised the use of 
                      embryological characters in taxonomy. He established the Department 
                      of Botany, University of Delhi as an important centre of research in 
                      embryology and tissue culture. He also emphasised the need for initiation 
                      of work on artificial culture of immature embryos. These days, tissue 
                      culture has become a landmark in science. His work on test tube 
PANCHANAN M AHESHWARI fertilisation and intra-ovarian pollination won worldwide acclaim.
     (1 904-1 966)       He was honoured with fellowship of Royal Society of London (FRS), 
                      Indian National Science Academy and several other institutions of 
                      excellence. He encouraged general education and made a significant 
                      contribution to school education by his leadership in bringing out the 
                      very first textbooks of Biology for Higher Secondary Schools published 
                      by NCERT in 1964.

CHAPTER 1            12083CHD1



REPRODUCTION IN ORGANISMS










 1 . 1 Asexual 
   Reproduction
 1.2 Sexual    Each and every organism can live only for a certain period 
   Reproductionof time. The period from birth to the natural death of an 
               organism represents its life span. Life spans of a few 
               organisms are given in Figure 1.1. Several other organisms 
               are drawn for which you should find out their life spans 
               and write in the spaces provided. Examine the life spans 
               of organisms represented in the Figure 1.1. Isn't it both 
               interesting and intriguing to note that it may be as short 
               as a few days or as long as a few thousand years? Between 
               these two extremes are the life spans of most other living 
               organisms. You may note that life spans of organisms are 
               not necessarily correlated with their sizes; the sizes of 
               crows and parrots are not very different yet their life spans 
               show a wide difference. Similarly, a mango tree has a much 
               shorter life span as compared to a peepal tree. Whatever 
               be the life span, death of every individual organism is a 
               certainty, i.e., no individual is immortal, except single-celled 
               organisms. Why do we say there is no natural death in 
               single-celled organisms? Given this reality, have you ever 
               wondered how vast number of plant and animal species 
               have existed on earth for several thousands of years? There 
               must be some processes in living organisms that ensure 
               this continuity. Yes, we are talking about reproduction, 
               something that we take for granted.

1                                                            BIOLOGY



            Elephant(    )             Rose (    )

  Dog       )            Butter fly ( 1-2 weeks)  Crow ( 15 years)


  Banana tree (  )


  Crocodile ( 60 years)      Horse (               Fruit fly ()


                )        Tortoise (100-150 years) Banyan tree ( )
               Figure 1.1 Approximate life spans of some organisms

                                      141


REPRODUCTION IN ORGANISMS

  Reproduction is defined as a biological process in which an 
organism gives rise to young ones (offspring) similar to itself. The offspring 
grow, mature and in turn produce new offspring. Thus, there is a cycle 
of birth, growth and death. Reproduction enables the continuity of the 
species, generation after generation. You will study later in Chapter 5 
(Principles of Inheritance and Variation) how genetic variation is created 
and inherited during reproduction.
  There is a large diversity in the biological world and each organism 
has evolved its own mechanism to multiply and produce offspring. 
The organism's habitat, its internal physiology and several other factors 
are collectively responsible for how it reproduces. Based on whether 
there is participation of one organism or two in the process of 
reproduction, it is of two types. When offspring is produced by a single 
parent with or without the involvement of gamete formation, the 
reproduction is asexual. When two parents (opposite sex) participate in 
the reproductive process and also involve fusion of male and female 
gametes, it is called sexual reproduction.

1.1 ASEXUAL REPRODUCTION
In this method, a single individual (parent) is capable of producing 
offspring. As a result, the offspring that are produced are not only 
identical to one another but are also exact copies of their parent. 
Are these offspring likely to be genetically identical or different? 
The term clone is used to describe such morphologically and 
genetically similar individuals.Bud








                                          Daughter 
                                           cells

                   (a)                     (b)
Figure 1.2 Cell division in unicellular organism: (a) Budding in 
       yeast; (b) Binary fission in Amoeba

  Let us see how widespread asexual reproduction is, among different 
groups of organisms. Asexual reproduction is common among 
single-celled organisms, and in plants and animals with relatively simple 
organisations. In Protists and Monerans, the organism or the parent 
cell divides by mitosis into two to give rise to new individuals (Figure1.2). 
Thus, in these organisms cell division is itself a mode of reproduction.

1

                                      BIOLOGY


                                    Conida












         (a)



















         (c)                 (d)

Figure 1.3 Asexual reproductive structures: (a) Zoospores of Chlamydomonas; (b) Conidia of 
     Penicillium; (c) Buds in Hydra; (d) Gemmules in sponge

         Many single-celled organisms reproduce by binary fission, where a 
         cell divides into two halves and each rapidly grows into an adult (e.g., 
         Amoeba, Paramecium). In yeast, the division is unequal and small 
         buds are produced that remain attached initially to the parent cell 
         which, eventually gets separated and mature into new yeast 
         organisms (cells). Under unfavourable condition the Amoeba withdraws 
         its pseudopodia and secretes a three-layered hard covering or cyst 
         around itself. This phenomenon is termed as encystation. When 
         favourable conditions return, the encysted Amoeba divides by multiple 
         fission and produces many minute amoeba or pseudopodiospores; 
         the cyst wall bursts out, and the spores are liberated in the surrounding 
         medium to grow up into many amoebae. This phenomenon is 
         known as sporulation.

                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           1


REPRODUCTION IN ORGANISMS

                                                                                                                                              Eyes
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Germinating Eye Buds                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     Buds




                                                                                                              (a)
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           (b)                                                       Adventitious                    Root
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Adventitious              Buds






                                                                      (c)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     (d)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        (e)

       Figure 1.4 Vegetative propagules in angiosperms: (a) Eyes of potato; (b) Rhizome of ginger;                  (c) Bulbil of Agave; (d) Leaf buds of Bryophyllum; (e) Offset of water hyacinth

                              Members of the Kingdom Fungi and simple plants such as algae 
reproduce through special asexual reproductive structures (Figure 1.3). 
The most common of these structures are zoospores that usually are 
microscopic motile structures. Other common asexual reproductive 
structures are conidia (Penicillium), buds (Hydra) and gemmules (sponge).
                              You have learnt about vegetative reproduction in plants in Class XI. 
What do you think - Is vegetative reproduction also a type of asexual 
reproduction? Why do you say so? Is the term clone applicable to the 
offspring formed by vegetative reproduction?
                              While in animals and other simple organisms the term asexual is used 
unambiguously, in plants, the term vegetative reproduction is frequently 
used. In plants, the units of vegetative propagation such as runner, 
rhizome, sucker, tuber, offset, bulb are all capable of giving rise to new 
offspring (Figure 1.4). These structures are called vegetative propagules.

                                BIOLOGY

     Obviously, since the formation of these structures does not involve two 
     parents, the process involved is asexual. In some organisms, if the body 
     breaks into distinct pieces (fragments) each fragment grows into an 
     adult capable of producing offspring (e.g., Hydra). This is also a mode 
     of asexual reproduction called fragmentation.
      You must have heard about the scourge of the water bodies or about 
     the 'terror of Bengal'. This is nothing but the aquatic plant 'water hyacinth' 
     which is one of the most invasive weeds found growing wherever there is 
     standing water. It drains oxygen from the water, which leads to death of 
     fishes. You will learn more about it in Chapters 13 and 14. You may find 
     it interesting to know that this plant was introduced in India because of 
     its beautiful flowers and shape of leaves. Since it can propagate vegetatively 
     at a phenomenal rate and spread all over the water body in a short period 
     of time, it is very difficult to get rid off them.
      Are you aware how plants like potato, sugarcane, banana, ginger, 
     dahlia are cultivated? Have you seen small plants emerging from the 
     buds (called eyes) of the potato tuber, from the rhizomes of banana and 
     ginger? When you carefully try to determine the site of origin of the new 
     plantlets in the plants listed above, you will notice that they invariably 
     arise from the nodes present in the modified stems of these plants. When 
     the nodes come in contact with damp soil or water, they produce roots 
     and new plants. Similarly, adventitious buds arise from the notches 
     present at margins of leaves of Bryophyllum. This ability is fully exploited 
     by gardeners and farmers for commercial propagation of such plants.
      It is interesting to note that asexual reproduction is the common method 
     of reproduction in organisms that have a relatively simple organisation, 
     like algae and fungi and that they shift to sexual method of reproduction 
     just before the onset of adverse conditions. Find out how sexual 
     reproduction enables these organisms to survive during unfavourable 
     conditions? Why is sexual reproduction favoured under such conditions? 
     Asexual (vegetative) as well as sexual modes of reproduction are exhibited 
     by the higher plants. On the other hand, only sexual mode of reproduction 
     is present in most of the animals.

     4 .2 SEXUAL REPRODUCTION
     Sexual reproduction involves formation of the male and female gametes, 
     either by the same individual or by different individuals of the opposite 
     sex. These gametes fuse to form the zygote which develops to form the 
     new organism. It is an elaborate, complex and slow process as compared 
     to asexual reproduction. Because of the fusion of male and female gametes, 
     sexual reproduction results in offspring that are not identical to the parents 
     or amongst themselves.
      A study of diverse organisms-plants, animals or fungi-show that
     though they differ so greatly in external morphology, internal structure

REPRODUCTION IN ORGANISMS

and physiology, when it comes to sexual mode of reproduction, 
surprisingly, they share a similar pattern. Let us first discuss what features 
are common to these diverse organisms.
  All organisms have to reach a certain stage of growth and maturity in 
their life, before they can reproduce sexually. That period of growth is 
called the juvenile phase. It is known as vegetative phase in plants. 
This phase is of variable durations in different organisms.
  The end of juvenile/vegetative phase which marks the beginning of 
the reproductive phase can be seen easily in the higher plants when they 
come to flower. How long does it take for marigold/ rice/ wheat/ coconut/ 
mango plants to come to flower? In some plants, where flowering occurs 
more than once, what would you call the inter-flowering period -juvenile 
or mature?
  Observe a few trees in your area. Do they flower during the same 
month year after year? Why do you think the availability of fruits like 
mango, apple, jackfruit, etc., is seasonal? Are there some plants that flower 
throughout the year and some others that show seasonal flowering? 
Plants-the annual and biennial types, show clear cut vegetative, 
reproductive and senescent phases, but in the perennial species it is very 
difficult to clearly define these phases. A few plants exhibit unusual 
flowering phenomenon; some of them such as bamboo species flower only 
once in their life time, generally after 50-100 years, produce large number 
of fruits and die. Another plant, Strobilanthus kunthiana (neelakuranji), 
flowers once in 12 years. As many of you would know, this plant flowered 
during September-October 2006. Its mass flowering transformed large 
tracks of hilly areas in Kerala, Karnataka and Tamil Nadu into blue 
stretches and attracted a large number of tourists. In animals, the juvenile 
phase is followed by morphological and physiological changes prior to 
active reproductive behaviour. The reproductive phase is also of variable 
duration in different organisms.
  Can you list the changes seen in human beings that are indicative 
of reproductive maturity?
  Among animals, for example birds, do they lay eggs all through the 
year? Or is it a seasonal phenomenon? What about other animals like 
frogs and lizards? You will notice that, birds living in nature lay eggs only 
seasonally. However, birds in captivity (as in poultry farms) can be made 
to lay eggs throughout the year. In this case, laying eggs is not related to 
reproduction but is a commercial exploitation for human welfare. The 
females of placental mammals exhibit cyclical changes in the activities of 
ovaries and accessory ducts as well as hormones during the reproductive 
phase. In non-primate mammals like cows, sheep, rats, deers, dogs, tiger, 
etc., such cyclical changes during reproduction are called oestrus cycle 
where as in primates (monkeys, apes, and humans) it is called menstrual 
cycle. Many mammals, especially those living in natural, wild conditions 
exhibit such cycles only during favourable seasons in their reproductive

                                     BIOLOGY

         phase and are therefore called seasonal breeders. Many other mammals 
         are reproductively active throughout their reproductive phase and hence 
         are called continuous breeders.
          That we all grow old (if we live long enough), is something that we 
         recognise. But what is meant by growing old? The end of reproductive 
         phase can be considered as one of the parameters of senescence or old 
         age. There are concomitant changes in the body (like slowing of 
         metabolism, etc.) during this last phase of life span. Old age ultimately 
         leads to death.
          In both plants and animals, hormones are responsible for the 
         transitions between the three phases. Interaction between hormones and 
         certain environmental factors regulate the reproductive processes and 
         the associated behavioural expressions of organisms.
         Events in sexual reproduction : After attainment of maturity, all sexually 
         reproducing organisms exhibit events and processes that have remarkable 
         fundamental similarity, even though the structures associated with sexual 
         reproduction are indeed very different. The events of sexual reproduction 
         though elaborate and complex, follow a regular sequence. Sexual 
         reproduction is characterised by the fusion (or fertilisation) of the male and 
         female gametes, the formation of zygote and embryogenesis. For convenience 
         these sequential events may be grouped into three distinct stages namely, 
         the pre-fertilisation, fertilisation and the post-fertilisation events.

          2.1 Pr fertilisation Events
         These include all the events of sexual reproduction prior to the fusion of 
         gametes. The two main pre-fertilisation events are gametogenesis and 
         gamete transfer.
         1.2.1.1 Gametogenesis
         As you are already aware, gametogenesis refers to the process of formation 
         of the two types of gametes - male and female. Gametes are haploid cells.












        (a)       (b)

Figure 1.5 Types of gametes: (a) Isogametes of Cladophora (an alga); (b) Heterogametes of 
     Fucus (an alga); (c) Heterogametes of Homo sapiens (Human beings)

